<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">quoteSalute</title>
            <title type="sub">Dokumentation</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>
                  <note>Team quoteSalute</note>
               </resp>
               <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1034877364">
                  <surname>Dumont</surname>
                  <forename>Stefan</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Klappenbach</surname>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Kullick</surname>
                  <forename>Marvin</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1121508855">
                  <surname>Neuber</surname>
                  <forename>Frederike</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Philipp</surname>
                  <forename>Luisa</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <surname>Pohl</surname>
                  <forename>Oliver</forename>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de">Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der
                  Wissenschaften</ref>
            </publisher>
            <idno type="url"
               >https://github.com/telota/salutesig/tree/master/doc/documentation_de.xml</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">This file is licensed
                  under the terms of the Creative Commons License CC-BY 4.0</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="a1">
            <head>About the Project</head>
            <p>quoteSalute offers inspiring greeting formulas from digital letter editions for your
               E-mail correspondence. The application thus creates a playful approach to the world
               of historical correspondences and enables the integration of academic Editions work
               in your everyday communication.</p>
            <p>quoteSalute was developed by a student project of Lou Klappenbach, Marvin Kullick and
               Louisa Philipp, supervised by Stefan Dumont, Frederike Neuber and Oliver Pohl in the
               Digital Humanities Working Group <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de/telota">TELOTA</ref>
               and the project <ref target="http:/correspSearch.net?l=en">"correspSearch - Letter
                  editions network"</ref> at the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and
               Humanities. </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a2">
            <head>Search Salutes</head>
            <p>On the website you can browse for greetings. If you do not like the greeting
               displayed, simply generate a new one by clicking on the orange refresh button. You
               can also use filters to narrow the search query according to your wishes. Once you
               have found the right greeting, you can copy it with the copy button. Open the e-mail
               program of your choice and then simply insert it into the next mail and send it!</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a3">
            <head>Text Corpus</head>
            <p>A curated corpus of greetings from various digital letter editions is the basis of
               quoteSalute. For this purpose, &lt;salute&gt; elements and associated bibliographical
               information were extracted automatically from the TEI-XML-files of the editions and
               stored into a new TEI-XML-file for each edition. During curating, the data was (1)
               cleared of of repetitions, inappropriate contents and very short greetings and (2)
               expaded by an own tagging to allow later filtering of the greetings. The greetings
               were tagged according to three criteria. First, it was determined whether the
               greeting is more formal or friendly in content. On the other hand, it was recorded,
               whether the gender of the sender and the receiver are apparent from the context (this
               was especially necessary for greetigns written in languages that classify words
               gender categories). And finally, the language was marked. This tagging allows the
               filter function and, together with the above-mentioned cleanup, makes a curation of
               the data necessary.</p>
            <p>The text corpus is currently fed by the following digital letter editions: </p>
            <list>
               <item> Aloys Hirt – Briefwechsel 1787–1837, ed. by Uta Motschmann.
                  Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin. URL: <ref
                     target="https://aloys-hirt.bbaw.de/">https://aloys-hirt.bbaw.de</ref>
               </item>
               <item> August Wilhelm Ifflands dramaturgisches und administratives Archiv. Digitale
                  Edition hrsg. Von Klaus Gerlach. Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der
                  Wissenschaften, Berlin. URL: <ref target="http://iffland.bbaw.de/"
                     >https://iffland.bbaw.de</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Briefe und Texte aus dem intellektuellen Berlin um 1800“. Hrsg. v. Anne
                  Baillot. Berlin: Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. URL: <ref
                     target="http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/"
                     >www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Briefwechsel Daniel Sanders im Deutschen Textarchiv, hg. v. Sebastian Göttel.
                  Berlin 2017-2018. URL: <ref
                     target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/sanders-briefe"
                     >http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/sanders-briefe</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Carl-Maria-von-Weber-Gesamtausgabe, Digitale Edition. URL: <ref
                     target="http://www.weber-gesamtausgabe.de"
                     >http://www.weber-gesamtausgabe.de</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Digitale Edition der Briefe Erdmuthe Benignas von Reuß-Ebersdorf (1670-1732),
                  hg. V. Prell, Martin u. Schmidt-Funke, Julia. Jena 2017 [Work in Progress]. URL:
                     <ref target="http://erdmuthe.thulb.uni-jena.de/"
                     >http://erdmuthe.thulb.uni-jena.de</ref>
               </item>
               <item> edition humboldt digital, hg. v. Ottmar Ette. Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie
                  der Wissenschaften, Berlin. URL: <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/"
                     >http://edition-humboldt.de</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Jean Paul Briefwechsel, Digitale Edition (basierend auf der III. Abteilung der
                  Historisch-kritischen Ausgabe, hg. v. Eduard Berend), Berlin-Brandenburgische
                  Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin 2018 <ref
                     target="http://www.bbaw.de/forschung/jean_paul/">[Veröffentlichung
                     demnächst]</ref>. </item>
               <item> Lebenswelten, Erfahrungsräume und politische Horizonte der ostpreußischen
                  Adelsfamilie Lehndorff vom 18. bis in das 20.Jahrhundert, ed. by Gaby Huch.
                  Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin. URL: <ref
                     target="http://lebenswelten-lehndorff.bbaw.de/"
                     >https://lebenswelten-lehndorff.bbaw.de/</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Marx-Engels-Gesamtausgabe digital, hg. von der Internationalen
                  Marx-Engels-Stiftung. Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin.
                  URL: <ref target="http://megadigital.bbaw.de/">http://megadigital.bbaw.de/</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Wilhelm von Humboldt - Sprachwissenschaftliche Korrespondenz. Hg. von der
                  Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin. URL: <ref
                     target="https://wvh-briefe.bbaw.de/">https://wvh-briefe.bbaw.de</ref>
               </item>
               <item> Fanny Lewald an Hermann Hettner - Briefe aus den Jahren 1847-1857. Hrsg. v.
                  Frederike Neuber. In: Berliner Beiträge zur Editionswissenschaft. Bd. 18. Hrsg: Jörg
                  Jungmayr u. Marcus Schotte. 2017.
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a10">
            <head>Background</head>
            <p>Salutations were (and are) essential elements of the written communication,
               especially of the letter. They point out, on the one hand, that letters display an
               "ad-hoc writtenness" and that they have a certain proximity to orality (Elspaß 2011,
               24 and 27), because the formal structure of a letter follows the conversation
               procedure: Turning to the partner - presentation of the information, the request etc.
               - and turning away from the partner (Nickisch 1991, 9-10). It was not without reason
               that letters were already understood in the 18th and 19th centuries as a
               "conversation among attendees", although in the end they are not a conversation, but
               only an attempt to replace it and are subject to specific conditions (Bürgel 1976,
               287-288; Reinlein 2003, 54-55).</p>
            <p>On the other hand, salutations serve as "indicators of the relationships that the
               author has or believes to have with the recipient" (Ermert 1979, 104). With regard to
               historical letters, they tell the modern reader something about the social
               relationship between sender and addressee - as long as one not only reads a single
               one, but several letters of correspondence. This allows informal salutations give an
               indication of a friendly relationship, while formal salutations point to a more
               distant relationship. Also professional or professional Differences in hierarchy are
               expressed in salutations of letters. Finally, salutations reveal as a personal form
               of address to the pen pal sometimes also the unspoken or "unwritten". If salutations
               for example shift from extremely cordially to distanced during the course of a
               correspondence, this could be interpreted as a sign that the relationship between the
               correspondents has cooled down without the possible disruption from the letter
               content must emerge.</p>
            <p>The adoption of salutations is therefore extremely important for letter editions. For
               these reasons, the guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative have long since offered
               an encoding option with the <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-salute.html"
                  >Element <hi rend="code">&lt;salute&gt;</hi></ref> (which, however, still has a
               few limitations such as the lack of being able to using <hi rend="code"
                  >&lt;salute&gt;</hi> in paragraphs (<hi rend="code">&lt;p&gt;</hi>)). Within
               quoteSalute exactly this coding is evaluated and displayed with further semantic
               information (degree of formality, gender, language).</p>
            <p>However, only the letter closing salutations were evaluated - not the opening
               salutations. This is due to the goal that the salutations should be supplied for the
               users own correspondence to spice up the communication - and not to to disturb it by
               inappropriate content. However, the latter would probably be the case if the opening
               salutation, i.e. the The second line, which the addressee reads after the subject,
               would be "historicized". Furthermore in the late 18th and 19th centuries it is also a
               fact that the salutation becomes shorter and shorter the more friendly the social
               relationship between the correspondents is - until in some cases they are completely
               omitted. For the purpose of quoteSalute this would of course be detrimental.</p>
            <p>Even though quoteSalute is first and foremost a playful handling of the material, it
               also shows the scientific and literary value of Greeting formulas in letters.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a4">
            <head>Technologies</head>
            <p>The generation of the salutations was implemented in a web application. This was
               realized with HTML, CSS and Javascript. In addition, we used the Front-End-Framework
               VueJS for data processing and for the dynamic exchange of HTML elements. Bootstrap
               was used to achieve a consistent design of the website. As database we used eXist db,
               the database query is done using XQuery and the response data is returned as
               JSON.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a9">
            <head>Participate</head>
            <p> You are working on a digital letter edition and think of the salutations of your
               Correspondence should also be included into quoteSalute? We are very happy to expand
               our dataset with new salutes. Any digital letter edition based on the TEI format can
               take part.</p>
            <p> For a participation of your project we need a TEI-XML file with the salutations from
               your digital letter edition. To make it as easy as possible for you to we provide an
                  <ref target="https://github.com/telota/quoteSalute/blob/master/doc/example.xml"
                  >example file</ref> and an empty <ref
                  target="https://github.com/telota/quoteSalute/blob/master/doc/template.xml"
                  >template file</ref> for you to download. In addition to the greeting formulas,
               your file should also contain associated bibliographical information (title of the
               edition, title of the letter) and a link to the web view of the respective letter in
               the digital edition. For technical details on creating the quoteSalute-compliant TEI
               XML file, please refer to the table below, in which the TEI elements and their
               functions are listed, as well as the comments in the template and example file. </p>
            <div xml:id="a6">
               <head>Enable Filtering</head>
               <p> If you want your greeting formulas to be searchable with the filter function, you
                  must check the contents of the greeting formulas. Each greeting formula is
                  assigned an attribute @ana, which indicates whether (1) the gender of sender*in
                  and/or recipient*in becomes apparent from the context of the greeting formula and
                  (2) the quotation is to be understood formally or amicably. You should also mark
                  out the language of the greeting formula. Otherwise your greeting formulas will
                  only be displayed if <hi rendition="#b">none</hi> filters are set! </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a7">
            <head>Coding</head>
            <p>The following tables provide detailed information about the structure of the TEI XML
               file required to include your greeting formulas in quoteSalute.</p>
            <table>
               <head>Meta data in the teiHeader</head>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell>XPath (relative to //teiHeader)</cell>
                  <cell>Description</cell>
                  <cell>Value(s) und Example(s)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/fileDesc/titleStmt/title</cell>
                  <cell>Title of the file. Should contain the name of your letter edition.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">&lt;salute&gt;-elements of "edition humboldt
                        digital"</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/fileDesc/titleStmt/respStmt</cell>
                  <cell>Specification of responsibility in &lt;note&gt;. The element
                     &lt;respStmt&gt; should have further &lt;persName&lt; elements with the names
                     of the creators.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">Collection and curation of data</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/fileDesc/noteStmt/note/<lb/>@type="data_integration"</cell>
                  <cell>Specification of when data was extracted from the edition and that a
                     selection was made.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">The data was taken over from &lt;ref
                        target="https://edition-humboldt.de"&gt;
                        https://edition-humboldt.de&lt;/ref&gt; on 15.3.2018. Later published
                        contents of the edition may be added in the future.</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/fileDesc/noteStmt/note/<lb/>@type="selection"</cell>
                  <cell>Specification that the greeting formulas from the edition have been curated
                     and edited.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">For quoteSalute, those salutes were selected that are
                        relevant for the application in terms of content, form and
                     length.</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/fileDesc/sourceDesc/bibl</cell>
                  <cell>Here the complete source reference of the edition is to be inserted.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">edition humboldt digital, ed. by Ottmar Ette.
                        Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin.</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/encodingDesc</cell>
                  <cell>The default encodingDescription must be inserted in the partHeader, which
                     declares the possible values for @ana. This taxonomy is predefined in the
                     template and can be copied directly without changes. See the table below for
                     more information.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code"/></cell>
               </row>
            </table>

            <table>
               <head>Salutations in //text</head>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell>XPath (Relative to //text)</cell>
                  <cell>Descrition</cell>
                  <cell>Value(s) and example(s)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div[@type="included"]</cell>
                  <cell>This div consists of the list of greeting formulas and the associated
                     bibliographic data.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div[@type="excluded"]/<lb/>listRef/ref/@target</cell>
                  <cell>This list consists of the links of the letters whose greeting formulas
                     should not be included in the body (e.g. because they are too short).</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">"edition-humboldt.de/H0015080"</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit</cell>
                  <cell>One or more &lt;cit&gt;-elements containing the greeting formulas and the
                     corresponding bibliographic information</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit/quote</cell>
                  <cell>The salutation as simple text, without quotation marks</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit/quote/@ana</cell>
                  <cell>Here the tagging for the speaking and the addressed gender as well as the
                     degree of formality is conducted. See also the taxonomy below.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">"#informal #s-f #r-m"</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row xml:id="note-language">
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit/quote/@xml:lang</cell>
                  <cell>Here the language of the greeting formula is recorded according to <ref
                        target="https://iso639-3.sil.org/code_tables/639/data/d">ISO-Code
                        639-3</ref>.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">"deu"</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit/title[@type="letter"]</cell>
                  <cell>Title of the letter from which the greeting formula originates, as it is
                     given in the respective edition.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit/title[@type="edition"]</cell>
                  <cell>Title of the edition from which the salutation originates.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="code">/div/cit/bibl/ref/@target</cell>
                  <cell>The @target contains the URL that links to the letter in the digital
                     edition.</cell>
                  <cell>E.g. <hi rend="code">"http://edition-humboldt.de/H0002656"</hi></cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>

         <div xml:id="a8">
            <head>Taxonomy</head>
            <div>
               <head>Formality</head>
               <p>Depending on whether the greeting formula is more formal or more informal, one of
                  the following values is selected:</p>
               <table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>Value</cell>
                     <cell>Description</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#formal</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation is formal.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#informal</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation is amicably.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Gender</head>
               <p>One of the following values can be set for the gender of the speaking or addressed
                  person (if apparent in the text):</p>
               <table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>Valute</cell>
                     <cell>Description</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#s-m</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation implies a male sender</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#s-f</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation implies a female sender</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#s-n</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation implies a neutral sender</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#r-m</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation implies a male receiver</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#r-f</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation implies a female receiver</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rend="code">#r-n</cell>
                     <cell>Salutation does not imply any gender of the receiver.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The language in which the salutation is written is also a filter option. It is
                  noted in <hi rend="code">quote/@xml:id</hi> (see <ref target="#note-language"
                     >above</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Examples of Annotation</head>
               <div>
                  <head>Examples 1</head>
                  <p>Salutation is in German, of formal character and does not imply a recognizable
                     gender for both sender and recipient.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="code">&lt;quote xml:lang="deu" ana="#formal #s-n #r-n"&gt;Bis dahin
                        empfiehlt sich Ihrem Wohlwollen hochachtungsvoll&lt;/quote&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Examples 2</head>
                  <p>Salutation is in German, informal in character and implies that the sender is
                     male and no gender can be specified for the recipient.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="code">&lt;quote xml:lang="deu" ana="#informal #s-m #r-n"&gt;Ihr
                        treuer Diener&lt;/quote&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Examples 3</head>
                  <p>Salutation is in German, of formal character and implies that the sender is
                     male and the recipient is female.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="code">&lt;quote xml:lang="lat" ana="#formal #s-m #r-f"&gt;Gottes
                        Segen über Sie, meine teure Mutter&lt;/quote&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Examples 4</head>
                  <p>Salutation is in English, of formal character and implies that the recipient is
                     male while there is no specification of the senders gender.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="code">&lt;quote xml:lang="eng" ana="#formal #s-n #r-m"&gt;Dear Sir
                        Faithfully yours&lt;/quote&gt;</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="a11">
            <head>Literature</head>
            <list>
               <item>Bürgel, Peter. 1976. „Der Privatbrief. Entwurf eines heuristischen Modells“.
                  Deutsche Vierteljahresschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und Geistesgeschichte 50:
                  281–97. </item>
               <item>Elspaß, Stephan. 2011. Sprachgeschichte von unten. Untersuchungen zum
                  geschriebenen Alltagsdeutsch im 19. Jahrhundert. Reihe Germanistische Linguistik
                  263. Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter.</item>
               <item>Ermert, Karl. 1979. Briefsorten : Untersuchungen zu Theorie und Empirie der
                  Textklassifikation. Reihe germanistische Linguistik 20. Tübingen: Niemeyer. </item>
               <item>Nickisch, Reinhard M. G. 1991. Brief. Sammlung Metzler. Realien zur Literatur,
                  Bd. 260. Stuttgart: Metzler. </item>
               <item>Reinlein, Tanja. 2003. Der Brief als Medium der Empfindsamkeit: erschriebene
                  Identitäten und Inszenierungspotentiale. Würzburg: Königshausen &amp; Neumann. </item>
               <item>TEI Consortium (Hg.). 2018. TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                  Interchange. [Version 3.3.0 vom 31. Januar 2018]. TEI Consortium. <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/</ref>.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
